Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 17; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Since his unfortunate return, has received two letters from Mr. Gourlade wherein it appears Franklin blames him for certain charges in the accounts against the United States; reasons why he ordered the articles in question; has no other motive than the advancement of the service. The "Ariel" will again be ready for sea in the course of a week.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 18; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Her opinion of Franklin's "Dialogue with the Gout"; begs him not to let M. Veillard, Abbé de la Roche, etc., touch up his French; thinks his style is weakened by the influence of grammarians.
    Printed in Proceedings of American Philosophical Society, XL, 103, and in Putnam's Monthly, October 1906, 35.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    The fertility of imagination displayed by the enemy in all that relates to America; advisability of authentic accounts. Enclosing papers giving particulars of Major [Patrick] Ferguson's defeat on King's Mountain, South Carolina. Some troops landed by the enemy at Portsmouth, Va., but are held there by the miltia. Congress has forbidden all short enlistments and voted an army of thirty-five thousand men for the war. As the affair of the late Adjutant-General of the British army [André] may be misrepresented, encloses proceedings; also an account which places Arnold's past character upon its proper footing. Transcribes a Resolve of Congress concerning the virtuous and patriotic conduct of three young men, [John] Paulding, [David] Williams and [Issac] Van Wart, in intercepting and making prisoner, Major John André. Mutual harmony and affection between the French and American troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 20; A.L.S. 5p.; Searle, James. Amsterdam
    Has no doubt that the news of Arnold's treason has come to hand; expresses his opinion of such base conduct and the motives for it; he has been sentenced to be publicily reprimanded by General Washington; is perfectly willing to have this letter quoted to support the truth of these charges.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 20; A.L.S. 1P.; Gourlade, -----. Paris
    Has been forced to remain longer in Paris than he had expected; wishes to know if this delay will make a difference regarding the letters to Capt. Jones confided to his care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade, -----. Paris
    Enclosing a letter just received from M. Moylan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 20; A.L.S. 5p.; Tende, —, comte de. Stuttgart
    Sends a letter to be forwarded to Baron Von Steuben concerning the manufacture of saltpetre in the United States. Desires, on his own account, the position of colonel of artillery, and for a friend the rank of major with certain emoluments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Fleury le jeune, — (pharmacist). Avranches
    Wishes to establish himself in the United States as a druggist.
  - to W.T. Franklin., 1780 November 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    From Paris. Details concerning the freighting of his vessel, the "Marquis de la Fayette"; his reasons for wishing her to sail directly from Bordeaux. Desires certain bills settled.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Guyetand, Claude Marie. Paris
    Has the honor of presenting to Franklin his first verses dedicated to liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Benaven, ---------. Paris
    M. [Pierre] Colombe, served with distinction in the United States, was taken prisoner; unable to procure his exchange, he desires a position in the French army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Deloigne, Pierre. Lille
    Wishes to send to America a young man who posses a thorough knowledge of handwriting and arithmetic.
  - to Ferdinand Grand, 1780 November 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Sees no objection to the proposal made by the Director-General of Finances that a letter of credit be drawn on Congress for the needs of the French troops; has no recollection of refusing a similar proposal made to him by Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 24; L.S. 1p.; Courter, Harmon. L'Orient
    Much obliged for M. de Chaumont's offers but his men not willing to go to Bordeaux; should M. de Chaumont give him the command of the vessel, his officers and men would then undertake the journey with pleasure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Has just received a letter from M. Gourlade, of which the enclosed [2 p., in French] is an extract; in consequence has written the within letters [3 p.] to the new Minister of Marine and M. de Chaumont, claiming prize-money for the "Bon Homme Richard" and the "Alliance," while under his command; if Franklin thinks these letters suitable, begs his influence to support them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 24; L.S. 2 p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Received Franklin's favor of the 13th inst. and has accepted the bills; if he does not succeed in his efforts to arrange a loan, will draw upon Franklin when they become payable; on his arrival believed that money might be had upon the credit of the United States; such a consummation prevented by the news from South Carolina and New York, and above all by the affair of the Burgomaster and Sir Joseph Yorke's memorial.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 25; A.L.S 1 p.; Valmont de Bomare, Jacques-Christophe
    Is about to begin his course of lectures; begs the honor of Franklin's presence at the first one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 26; A.L.S. 2 p.; Kalb, Mlle — de (Johann's sister). Steudal
    Was much moved to see in the Gazette the death of her brother, General de Kalb(e); as she is his only near, surviving relative, begs to be informed what possessions her brother left in America and in what way she may obtain them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780 November] 26; A.L. 1 p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sending notes or coments on a dialogue written in French by Franklin. Thinks he expresses himself more forcefully than would a grammarian. Remains Franklin of his promise to give her a printed copy of his works.
    Printed in Proc. Am. Phill. Soc., XL,108.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 26; L.S. 2 p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Concerning the Resolutions of Congress ordering drafts upon Franklin; astonished at being asked for the necessary funds to meet them will endeavor to procure for him next year the same aid he has been able to furnish during the present one.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 515).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 27; A.L.S. 1 p.; Harmand,------. Paris
    Hopes Franklin will help him to go to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 28; L.S. 2p.; Jacques François Crespin and Aimable Titoix. Dunkirk
    Served with Capt. Conyngham on the "Revenge"; have been deprived of their share of the prize-money and also their pay for nearly three years, during which time they languished in English prisons; beg for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Dispute between M. de Chaumont and himself decided in his favor. Two gentlemen of his own appointing (M. Rozée and M. Montaudouin) have decided the freight to be payable only after the goods are loaded at l'Orient and Messrs. Jauge and Co. (Mr. de Chaumont's correspondents) of Bordeaux, have, of their own accord, reduced the measurement of the ship to a reasonable tonnage. Requests him to send his dispatches for the "Mars" by return of post as she will by that time be ready to sail. The "Hercules," Captain [John] Carey, bound to Baltimore, of sixteen guns and eighty men, will sail with the "Mars."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 28; D. 5p.; The Continental Congress
    Extract from the instructions to B[enjamin] Franklin.
    (Press copy.)
    Printed in Diplom. Corres. of Am. Rev., Wharton, IV, 163.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Rouge, -----
    Begs Franklin to send him the corrected proof.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 November 30; L.S. 4p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Franklin's financial burdens. Mr. Searle's sanguine picture of American affairs. Affairs in Holland. A gentleman in Amsterdam commissioned by England to hire as many vessels as he possibly can to carry troops to America.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 518).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 November 30; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    M. [de] Mauduit [Duplessis] will be at her house Wednesday evening with an officer who desires to meet Franklin. This officer had captured an English vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Holland's agreement to an armed neutrality; resolution disapproving and disavowing Amsterdam's letter as to an eventual treaty between America and Holland; the Holland Assembly deliberating on the answer to be given to Sir Joseph Yorke's insolent memoir.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 1; L.S. 2p.; Courter, Harmon. L'Orient
    Did not think it right to keep his crew until the present date at thier owner's expense; has found places for most of them on American vessels. If the gentleman will give him the command of the cutter mentioned, will set out for Dunkirk at once with his officers, and has no doubt of meeting with success; is well acquainted with the coast of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Charretié, John. Paris
    Sends report from the Commitee of the House of Commons relative to French and Spanish prisoners. Hopes, with Franklin's assistance, to obtain the agency for the inspection of prisoners in Great Britain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. L'Orient
    Mr. Robert Mease, of Alexander, Va., proposes to visit several places in France and to pass some time in Paris; recommends him to Franklin's civility and protection; the devotion of Mr. Mease and his family to the great cause of liberty is well-known.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Destouches, -----. Dunkirk
    Acknowledging Franklin's kindness in endeavoring to obtain Capt. Courter and his crew for the privateer of M. Salomes; desires to name this vessel after Franklin; inspiration of such a title.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Mouret, Jno. Havre-de-Grace
    Just from an English prison; was Surgeon on the "Morris" and the "Retaliation"; the salary still due him; begs for assistance and employment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 3; A.L.S. 3p.; Lunier, Joseph. Havre-de-Grace
    Taken prisoner in January, 1777; made his escape on the 23d ult. from Forton prison; hoped to find an American Agent at Havre who would advance him a small sum, but was disappointed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 4; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Beaumarchais, Pierre-Augustin Caron de. Paris
    Enclosing a letter just arrived from England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 4; A.L.S. 5p.; von Esch, Johann Thaddeus. Augsburg
    Wishes employment for himself and six sons as agents and correspondents in German cities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Commodore Jones only waiting for Franklin's despatches to set sail; beg that they may be forwarded at once.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Has been ready for sea these five days past and only waiting for Franklin's despatches; hopes also for despatches from Court in consequence of advices received from Rhode Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 24th of October; laid the account of prisoners released before the Board of Sick and Hurt; still forty-one prisoners due, and no more exchanges until that debt is paid; account of the expenditure of one hundred pounds, received from M. Grand for the relief of prisoners; one hundred more lately committed to Forton; nothing further to be expected from public subscriptions; men afraid to show common sentiments of humanity towards Americans. Sorry to announce the death of their mutual friend, Mr. [Thomas] Bentley; much regretted by the old Club.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Has been entirely occupied in the contemplation of Nature; principally in regard to the influence of the vegetable kingdom upon the animal, and with the essential ingredients out of which the atmosphere is composed; intends soon to lay before the public the result of these experiments; explains his change of opinion on the effect on air caused by vegetables. Has made use of the several metal wires given him; details his method of employing them; will make no further use of this investigation save what Franklin, who furnished the materials and suggested the method of inquiry, may think proper. Desires to know if his book was well received in France; German and Dutch translations published. The Emperor prevented from seeing his experiments by the death of His Majesty's mother. Wishes to hear news of America and explanation of Arnold's treachery.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Fleury and Demadières. Orleans
    Repaired the cases of Madeira and forwarded them to Passy; recommending their wine and furnishing prices.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Couder, J. M. Nancy
    Offers to provide the army with everything necessary in time of war, at a most reasonable figure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Congratulating him on the recovery of his health. Will be glad to see the details of Arnold's conduct; blames Congress and court-martials for inflicting slight punishment on criminals and then entrusting them with commands and employment; advises suing such knaves at common law; Arnold's case in point; the villain's bravery and baseness. Rumor of Gates obtaining an advantage over Cornwallis. The papers give out that M. Rochambeau has come to solicit more troops; the great need is for ships and money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 7; L.S. 1p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Enclosing bills of exchange for the use of S[amuel] C[ooper] Johonnot which he begs Franklin to take charge of.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The King of Prussia's influence in bringing about Holland's agreement to an armed neutrality. Proper time to enter their claim relative to the vessel carried off at Saba. Desiring a detailed account of Arnold's treason.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Magellan (Magalhaens), Jean-Hyacinthe de.
    Encloses the extract which he made longer than Mr. Vaughan's in order that it might be easily understood in French; it will appear in the Journal de Paris after being read at the Academy; desires Franklin to make any changes in it he may deem advisable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Pothonnier and Cie. Paris
    Mr. Gourlade not yet gone; return the three packets that they may be forwarded by an earlier opportunity; one of them for Mr. Jones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Enclosing three letters for Henry Laurens, which were to have been forwarded to Amsterdam; has heard of Mr. Laurens's unfortunate capture, therefore sends them to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Ruthardt, Gottlob Friederich. Ludwigsburg, Würtemberg
    Acknowledges Dr. Franklin's answer of November 14. Encloses three identical letters to Evangelical Lutheran Ministers at Philadelphia, and two letters from relatives of his, with request to forward.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 11; L.S. 2p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    An account of the entire affair in regard to the loading of his vessel, the "Marquis de la Fayette"; blames Franklin's nephew, Mr. Williams, for his interference; encloses certain papers and begs that no time may be lost before coming to some arrangement; his interests suffer cruelly by such delays.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Charretié, John. Paris
    Asking that the bearer be given the petition to the Minister of the Marine and the Report of the Committee of the House of Commons. Desires a few lines of introduction to Franklin's friends at Versailles. Mr. Pecholier, whom he proposes in the petition as his associate, is in one of the first houses in London.
    A.E. by Franklin setting forth M. Charretié's good character.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Collignon, -----. Dieuze
    Wishes to know if an important and interesting packet sent to Franklin through another person, has been received.
    A.E. by Franklin. Acknowledge receipt of letter and request to know the subject of the packet, as many are received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 11; A.L.S. 3p.; La Clause, Henry Jasme. Morlaix
    Served the United States from March, 1776 to July, 1780; his health obliged him to leave; encloses papers for certification to prove the truth of his statements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Boulainvilliers, ----- Anne-Gabriel-Henri Bernard, marquis de
    Forwards a little memoir, and desires Franklin to write his answers upon the margin; hopes his importunity may be pardoned on account of his sincere attachment to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 12; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Fresh difficulties started at Bordeaux; encloses copy of his letter [4 p., in French] to Messrs. Jauge and fils urging the necessity for the speedy departure of the "Marquis de la Fayette". Quantity of arms on board the "Mars".
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Intends sending a courier to Nantes, who will return at the end of the week with the decision of the Arbitrators; believes it will be the same as that of Bordeaux.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 13; A.L.S. 4p.; De Tousard, Lt Col Louis. Paris
    Wishes to return to the United States where he has already fought through two campaigns and been seriously wounded; has chosen as his intermediary, M. de Chaumont, who knows his zeal for the great cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 13; L.S. 3p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    The enemy have gone into winter quarters and by their position effectually cover the State of New Jersey; their refusal to fight; have improved every occasion of striking at them on a smaller scale. Major [Benjamin] Tallmadge's brilliant dash into Long Island and his safe return with four officers and fifty privates prisoners. Letter from Gen. Gates reports a new advantage obtained in South Carolina by Sumter; the enemy do not possess a single post east of Georgetown or north of Camden. British corps under Gen. Leslie have abandoned hope of a junction by land with Cornwallis; every one of their plans in this campaign defeated. The states exerting themselves in order that an army may soon take the field.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 14 and 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Jones, Peter Faneull. Dunkirk
    Sailed in the "Alliance" a year before; Capt. Jones put him in command of a Dutch prize with orders to proceed to Philadelphia; taken prisoner by the English and after many vicissitudes, made his escape; is penniless; begs for assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Halder and Co. Strasbourg
    At the request of a correspondent, they forward the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Summoned by M. de Montaudouin to answer his interrogatories; thinks this second decision will be doubly in his favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    No answer to be made to Sir Joseph Yorke's insolent memoir; hears that he is about to present a second; its contents. Reasons why his stay in Amsterdam is advisable. Desires to take the oath of allegiance to the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Wishes Franklin's opinion as regards Mr. Samuel Wharton's probity and punctuality in business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Waterhouse, Benjamin. Leyden
    Encloses letters brought with him from London; sorry for unavoidable delay. Dr. Fothergill's intention of writing to Franklin by a private hand; his opinions of the present state of affairs. Proposes going to Boston and exercising his profession there; believes it is not so necessary for men to go to Europe in order to cure the diseases of their next door neighbor; learnt many things during his stay with Dr. Fothergill. Read with interest the French medical work Franklin gave him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 18; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    The "Ariel" will be under sail at daybreak; neither Mr. Gourlade nor M. de La Grave have yet appeared; enloses receipt for arms; is taking ninety days' provisions. Had [Arthur] Lee and his cabal in the "Alliance" been in Heaven, the "Ariel," would have been no additional expense, and,with the "Alliance", would have carried the greatest part of the winter clothing for our army. Not surprised at the few desertions; encloses list of the present crew.
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont., 1780 December 19; A.L.S. 1p.; De Tousard, Lt. Col. Louis. Paris
    Gives his address.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Branco, ------. Paris
    Encloses the papers relative to the Portuguese prize, which the Captain desires to have legalized; encloses memoir in case it be thought necessary to forward it to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Destouches, -----. Dunkirk
    Announcing the arrival of the cutter "Franklin"; a most beautiful vessel. No news of Capt. Courter, but M. Salomes has found an excellent substiute, who will forward his papers at once, as they are anxious to sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Grand, Henry. Paris
    Arrived at Passy to find that Franklin had left for Versailles. Two enclosures; one, a copy in French of a letter from M. Necker to M. Grand (2p., in French) concerning a letter of credit; the other, from Mr. Franklin to M. Grand (1p.) concerning money matters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 20; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1 p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolution that the Minister at United States, at St. Petersburg, be furnished with letters of credit upon the Minister at Versailles to the amount of fifteen hundred pounds.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 20; A.L.S. 5p.; Führer. Felsberg
    His son promoted to the rank of Lieutenant-Colonel; eager to show his gratitude and appreciation; offers his services to the United States even at his advanced age.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Neufville, Leendert de. Amsterdam